Guide to the Harold Cruse Papers TAM.187
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
Harold Cruse Papers
Bulk, 1970-1985
1943-1994
TAM.187
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
10.25 linear feet in 12 boxes
Harold Cruse was born in 1916 in Petersburg, VA and is an African American author and professor best known for his Crisis of the Negro Intellectual (1967), a Marxist-nationalist critique of the Communist movement and an endorsement of an autonomous and revolutionary Black culture. He joined the Communist Party in 1947 (remaining a member for some seven years) and contributed to its newspaper, the Daily Worker. In the late 1960s, Cruse joined the faculty of the University of Michigan at Ann Arbor, and helped found their Center for Afro-American and African Studies. The collection includes articles (published and unpublished), correspondence from, among others, John Conyers, Langston Hughes, Manning Marable, and Wole Soyinka; also included is ephemera, lecture notes, and correspondence relating to the Eldridge Cleaver Legal Defense Fund, and Robert Williams.
Cruse, Harold
Custodial History note
Harold Cruse initially donated his papers to the Virginia Commonwealth University Special Collections and Archives in 1994. In 1995 the deed agreement between the two parties was mutually voided and the materials were returned to Dr. Cruse, who then donated them to Tamiment Library in 1996. The accession number associated with this gift is 1996.002. Additional materials were sent by Ivana Kukic in 2011. The accession number associated with these materials is 2011.104.
Additional correspondence was found in the repository and added to the collection in 2014. The accession number associated with this material is 2014.045.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Harold Cruse, an African American author and professor is best known for his Crisis of the Negro Intellectual (1967), a Marxist-nationalist critique of the Communist movement's influence and a call for an autonomous and revolutionary Black culture. Cruse was born in 1916 in Petersburg, Virginia. As a young child he moved to New York City with his father, where graduated from high school, held a variety of jobs prior to World War II, and then he served in the army in Italy. Following his discharge, he briefly attended City College. Cruse took classes at the Communist Party's George Washington Carver school in Harlem, joined the Party in 1947 (remaining a member for some seven years), and contributed drama and literature reviews to its newspaper, the Daily Worker. Cruse wrote four plays during the 1950s, but none were produced, and thereafter he concentrated on nonfiction. In the late 1960s, Cruse joined the faculty of the University of Michigan at Ann Arbor, and helped found their Center for Afro-American and African Studies. Cruse's other books are: Rebellion or Revolution? (1968), a set of essays on Black nationalism, Plural but Equal (1987), a critique of the effects of integration, and The Essential Harold Cruse: A Reader (2002).
Scope and Content Note
Notable correspondents in series one include: John Conyers, Cheikh Anta Diop, Jay Gorney, Langston Hughes, Manning Marable, Adolph Reed Jr., and Wole Soyinka. There is also one file of World War II-era letters to Cruse, and several thick files of academic correspondence. Series two contains ephemera, lecture notes, and some correspondence relating to Cruse's activity as a public intellectual, including files on the Eldridge Cleaver Legal Defense Fund, and on Robert Williams. Series three contains numerous article-length unpublished and published writings, book and theater reviews, and an almost complete typescript of the Crisis of the Negro Intellectual.
NOTE: As of March 2011, box 1 is undergoing preservation work, and is thus not available to researchers.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into four series: I, Correspondence; II, Topical Files, II, Writings; IV, Addendum (unprocessed).
Folders are generally arranged alphabetically within each series, though some correspondence is arranged chronologically.
I. Correspondence
II. Topical Files
III. Writings
IV. Addendum (unprocessed)
Conyers, John, 1929-; Cruse, Harold; Diop, Cheikh Anta; Gorney, Jay, 1896-1990; Marable, Manning, 1950-; Reed, Adolph L., 1947-; Soyinka, Wole.; African American authors.; African American communists.; African American journalists.; African Americans |x Civil rights.; Communists |z United States.; Correspondence.; Ephemera.; Lecture notes.; Manuscripts for publication.; Marxist criticism.; Reviews (document genre)
- Series I. Correspondence
  - Subseries A: Alphabetical NOTE: However, as of March 2011, box 1 is undergoing preservation work, and is thus not available to researchers.
    - Academic, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Academic, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Academic, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Academic, 1973-1990 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Afro-American Historic Association Niagara Frontier, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Afro-American Realty Corporation, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - American Literary Association, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - American Security Council, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Antioch College, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Association of African Historians, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Bahai National Information Office, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Bergman Publishers, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Black Books Bulletin, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Booker, Sue, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Congress on Research and Dance, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Conyers, John Jr. - Congressman, 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Cook, William ( Talking Drum Cable Television Program), 1986, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Diggs, Charles C. Jr., Congressman, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Diop, Cheikh Anta, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Diop, M Alioune, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Greene, Vera, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Fabre, Genevieve, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Fitchue, Leah Gaskin, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Fontenat, Chester, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Fulton, Richard (Lecture Agent), 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Gorney, Jay, 1950, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Handwritten (Miscellaneous), 1968-1988 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Hare, Nathan, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Haynes, Eugene - Musician, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Higginson, John E., 1988 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Howard University, 1976-1980 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Hughes, Langston, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Institute for Historical Review, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Institute for People Enterprises, undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Johnson, Cliff - Black Americans International Intercultural Organization, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Jones, Mack - Prairie View University, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Liberation Magazine, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Locke, Rovan G, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Marable, Manning, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - McClusky, John - Indiana University Press, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Moore, Carlos, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Negro History, Conference On, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - New York Times, 1968-1979 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Norman, Fred, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Reed, Adolph Jr., 1986 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Schmeri, Rudi, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Socialist Scholars Conference, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Soyinka, Wole, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - SUNY - David Nielson Tenure Review, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Story, Ralph, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Taylor, Clyde, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Thorpe, Earl E., 1978-1980 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Wacker, Fred, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Walter, Ronald, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Walton, Haynes, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Washington, University of, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Weitz, Marvin, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - William Monroe Trotter Institute, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - William Morris Agency, 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - William Morrow and Company Publishers, 1965-1976 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Wynter, Sylvia, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - World War II-era Letters to Cruse, 1943-1947 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Subseries B. Chronological
    - Correspondence, 1952-1957 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 1962-1993 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Series II. Topical Files
  - African American Museum, 1977-1987 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - African World, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - AfroAmerican Communicator, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Afro Arts Theater, 1955, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - American Negro Arts Festival, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - American Society of African Culture - "The Negro Writer and his Relationship to his Roots", 1959 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - AMSAC (American Society for African Culture) Writers Conference - Notes, ca. late 1950s (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Association of American University Presses, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Association for the Study of Afro American Life and History, 1976-1988 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Black American Music Symposium (Cruse's Notes as Moderator), 1985 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Black Law Students Alliance - Discussion Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Black Party: Founding Convention, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Black Scholar, 1969-1989 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Blacks in Predominantly White Colleges and Universities, The First National Think Tank On, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Bubbling Brown Sugar, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - California State University, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Carleton College, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Caucus of Black Sociologists (Includes Lecture Notes), 1975 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Center for Afro American and African Studies, 1981-1986 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Center for Soviet and East Europe Studies, 1976-1986 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Citizens for Community Development, 1978, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Cleveland State - Drimmer, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Contract for Article on "Key Issues in the Afro-American Experience - Part Two", 1969 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Cleaver, Eldridge (Legal Defense Fund, Other), 1969-1981 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Cornell University, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Course Outlines - Afro American Studies (Course 201 and 202), ca.1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Declaration of Black Intellectuals and Scholars in Support of the People's Struggle of West Papua New Guinea and East Timor Against Indonesian Colonialism, undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Harvard University - Alain Locke Symposium, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Harvard University - William Seymour Society Lectures, 1982-1985 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - History 572 - Course Description, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Indiana, University of (re: Promotion of Herman Hudson, and Minority Studies Program, 1977-1978 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Institute for People Enterprises (Conference on Urban Choices for Survival), 1979 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Institute of Scientific Information, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - In these Times, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - International Association for Cultural Freedom, 1971, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Iowa, University of - Lecture (re: Paul Robeson), 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Jefferson School of Social Science - Marxism and the Negro Question, undated (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Macalester College - Hubert Humphrey Lecture Notes, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Moore, Steven, undated (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Morgan State University Lecture (Includes Notes), 1975-1978 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - "Moynihan Report, A Statement on the", undated (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - National Conference of Artists - Lecture: Black Art in the 1930's, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities - American Culture Panel, 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - National Urban League, 1975-1978 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - New Dimensions, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - News of the Emeriti - Harold Cruse, undated (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Olive Harvey College - Speech, 1977-1988 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Owens, Leslie - The Dismissal of, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Pennsylvania, University of, 1986-1988 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Princeton University, 1976, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Sacramento Working Conference on the Black Political Party, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - "Separate but Equal" - International Institute of Flint (Lecture Notes), 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Stanford University Speech, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Studies on the Left, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - United Negro and Allied Veterans of America - New York State Council, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Virginia Commonwealth University, 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Wayne State University Humanities Conference, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Williams, Robert, 1961-1986 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - World War Two Memorabilia, 1941-1947 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Series III. Writings
  - "Aesthetic Theory of American Negritude", undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Afro American Communicator, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Afro American Youth Cultural Conference, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - "American Negritude", undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - American Negritude - Exploratory Philosophical Notes - Part II, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - "The American Negro and the Cuban Revolution", undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - "The American Negro Manifesto on Cultural Revolution", undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Article on: Negro in the Theater, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - "Assimilation in American Life" (Review by Cruse), 1964 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Baldwin, James - Articles About, undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - "Battle of Montreal" - African Heritage Studies Association, undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - "Behind the Black Power Movement", undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - "Black Anti-Semitism", undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Black Anti-Semitism - Notes on, 1985-1986 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - "Black Bourgeois", undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - "The Black Political Process - Myth or Reality - A Theoretical Analysis", 1978 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - "Black Studies: Interpretation, Methodology, and the Relationship to Social Movements", undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - "Bohemia Revisited", undated (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Book Review by Cruse of Freedom Song: A Personal Story of the 1960's Civil Rights Movement, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Book Review by Cruse of Introduction to Black Studies, by Maulana Karenga, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Book Reviews by Cruse (Miscellaneous), 1950-1964 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - "Charles Riley and New Negro Renaissance", undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - "A Chess Manual for the 'Potzers' by the Master Monsieur Fred Duval" - As Told by Cruse, ca. late 1950s-early 1960s (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Cleaver, Eldridge: The Fire this Time? (Review of) by Cruse, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - "Contemporary Dialectics", ca.1963 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - "The Creative and Performing Arts and the Struggle for Identity and Credibility", undated (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Crisis of the Negro Intellectual (ts; pp. 20-116), undated (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Crisis of the Negro Intellectual (ts; pp. 117-254), undated (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Crisis of the Negro Intellectual (ts; pp. 255-379), undated (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Crisis of the Negro Intellectual (ts; pp. 380-592), undated (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Crisis of the Negro Intellectual - "Black Nationalism and American Socialism" (by Eugene Genovese), 1968 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Crisis of the Negro Intellectual - Critique (by Bob Higgins), 1978 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Crisis of the Negro Intellectual - Twentieth Anniversary, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - "Cuba and the North American Negro", undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - "Cuba and the North American Negro: A Study in Two Revolutionary Perspectives", undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - "Cuba, Marxism, Nationalism, and the American Negro", undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - "Culture and the Negro Question" - Review by Cruse, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - "Cultural Identity and the Afro American", undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - "Death of White Sociology, Outline for", 1975 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - "The Delta Rose", undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - "The Education of a Rebel," Part One, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - "The Education of a Rebel," Part Two, undated (Box 4, Folder 8A)
  - "The Education of a Rebel," Part Three, undated (Box 4, Folder 8B)
  - "The Education of a Rebel," Part Four, undated (Box 4, Folder 8C)
  - "The Education of a Rebel," Part Five, undated (Box 4, Folder 8D)
  - "The Education of a Rebel," Part Six, undated (Box 4, Folder 8E)
  - "The Education of a Rebel," Part Seven, undated (Box 4, Folder 8F)
  - "The Education of a Rebel," Part Eight, undated (Box 4, Folder 8G)
  - "The Education of a Rebel," Part Nine, undated (Box 4, Folder 8H)
  - "The Education of a Rebel," Part Ten, undated (Box 4, Folder 8I)
  - "Force and Violence: from Monroe to Watts", undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - "From Shibe Park to Yankee Stadium", undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - "George Capdeville's Ancestry", undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - "Historical Roots of Social Change and Social Theory", undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - "Historical Roots of Social Change and Social Theory" (Handwritten), undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - "The House He Once Lived in", 1950 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - "The House He Used to Live in", 1949 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - "The Intellectuals and Force and Violence", undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - "Interludes with Duke Ellington", ca.1982-1985 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - London Diary, 1969-1970 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - "Marxism and Negritude", undated (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - "Marxism and Negritude Part Three", undated (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - "Marxism and Negro Literature", undated (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - "Marxism and the Negro Question", undated (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - "Memoirs of a Self-Taught Journalist", undated (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - "My Jewish Problem and Theirs", 1969 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Negro Culture: Heritage and Weapon (Review by Cruse), undated (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - "A Negro Looks at Cuba", undated (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - "The Negro Playwright", undated (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - "The Negro Writer - Disarmed, Dis[en]franchised, Disoriented", 1967 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - "The New Afro Americanism", undated (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - "The New Negro History of John Hope Franklin", 1980, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Notebooks / Journals (2), undated (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Notes: Robeson book, undated (Box 4, Folder 32a)
  - "On Explaining Twentieth Century Negro History", undated (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - "On Robert Brustein's Theater Visions", 1979 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Plural But Equal - Review of, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - "The Politics of Negro Business", undated (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - "A Preface to Leadership", undated (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - "Problems in Black Political Philosophy - Exploratory Paper" (Delivered at Morgan State University), 1978 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - "Proposal for a Collected Edition of the Essays", undated (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - "Race and Bohemians in Greenwich Village", 1960 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - "Race Riots and Remedies", 1964 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Rebellion or Revolution - Review of, undated (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Simply Heavenly and Stella Holt - A Viewpoint, undated (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - "The Sociology of Afro Americanism", undated (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Teaching and Sharing the Humanities: A College for Human Services Value Conference, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - "Three Faces West" - A Western Film Scenario (by Cruse), undated (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Untitled Typescript - "Despite many new features of the present day Negro rebellion, this rebellion has its roots in the accumulated experiences of the past fifty years...", undated (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Untitled Typescript - re: CAUSA and Negroes (pp 173-240), undated (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Untitled Typescript - "'The Crisis of the Negro Intellectual' was first published...", undated (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Untitled Typescript - re: Freedom Now Party, William Worthy, etc., undated (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Untitled Typescript - "In addition, we are being told by the white left...", undated (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Untitled Typescript - "In 1940, in one of my first acts in the pursuit of becoming a more 'social' being...", undated (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Untitled Typescript - "In 1964, the special Freedom ways Harlem issue was enlarged...", undated (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Untitled Typescript - "It was June in Italy, 1944, a languorous summer's day, when Juddie Jones, Negro truck driver, US Army, returned...", undated (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Untitled Typescripts - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Untitled Typescript - re: "Marxism and the Negro", undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Untitled Typescript - "The nearest living contact I have ever had with French culture was in North Africa during World War Two...", undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Untitled Typescript - "When the Socialist Workers Party (Trotskyist) announced in New York on January 14 that it had nominated a Negro...", undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Village Voice Editorial - "Reading Michael Harrington's report on the Vancouver meeting...", undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - What is a Program, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - What is Nationalism, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - "Where the Hummingbird Flies" - A Critique, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Series IV. Addendum 1 (unprocessed)
      - BOX 6
      - BOX 7
  - "Why an Afro American Cultural Philosophy is Necessary Today", undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Series V. Addendum 2: 2011 (unprocessed)
  - Box 8
  - Box 9
  - Box 10
  - Box 11 (0.5 linear ft.): Plays. Includes: The Black and the Red (re African American Communists and the Spanish Civil War, c. 1995); A Lady of Consequence: A Musical Play, 1962); Of Marms and Maids: A Drama in Two Acts, 1963); Untitled longer play set around beginning of 20th century.
  - Box 12 (0.5 linear ft.): Photographs. Includes loose and framed photos, negatives, historical postcards. There is a group portrait including Fidel Castro and one African American male; photos from trip(s) to Africa; and a photo of a lynching, allegedly from 1980.